<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>随想 on Mr.Zhou 博客</title>
    <link>https://kivinchoa.github.io/oneblog/tags/%E9%9A%8F%E6%83%B3/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 随想 on Mr.Zhou 博客</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 14:35:58 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://kivinchoa.github.io/oneblog/tags/%E9%9A%8F%E6%83%B3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>香港理工大学付教授讲座</title>
      <link>https://kivinchoa.github.io/oneblog/posts/lectfu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 14:35:58 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kivinchoa.github.io/oneblog/posts/lectfu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;今天上午10点听了来自香港理工大学机械工程系付教授的讲座，“如何从研究到发表高水平论文”，深受启发。以下几点非常值得借鉴：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1、Do not reinvent the wheel. (不要重复别人的研究过程与结果)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2、Do not prove the common-sense by using new cases. (不要使用新示例以证明常识性的结论)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3、Aim high, shoot high. (站得高，才能看得远)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4、Input and output relationship (is it the direct correlation?) (寻求输入与输出的关系)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5、Never complicate the simple relationship. (千万不要把简单问题复杂化)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6、Create new concept, terminology, term, algorithm, and systematic knowledge system. (形成一些新的术语、名词、算法及系统化的知识体系)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;文章的Highlights通常包括3到5点，绝不能有废话，每一个词得要精简再精简，要在5分钟之内吸引住审稿人。主要内容包括两个方面&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1、Action and findings (采用什么方法获得了什么发现，前者介绍不能超过20%)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2、Leaves and flowers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;全部的行为要讲究三个方面的流畅，逻辑流畅、技术流畅和语言流畅（Logical flow, technical flow, and language flow）。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;摘要、引言及结论中的结论性语句有本质的区别，摘要中的要抽象，模糊，不具体，定位要高，相当于要吊得起胃口，引言中突出文章的关注点，结论中的要突出具体、可操作的结论。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;另外，文章投稿后，杂志社第一步筛选的方法是crosscheck，看已有文献的重复率，所以引用论文的语句一定要谨慎，否则直接拒没商量。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>民办初中，是谁给了你“掐尖”的权利</title>
      <link>https://kivinchoa.github.io/oneblog/posts/edu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Apr 2018 12:07:44 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kivinchoa.github.io/oneblog/posts/edu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;4月28日注定是要载入西安初等教育史册的一天，这一天西安出台了民办初中的招生办法，摇号加面谈，两者比例为4：6。这一看似公平的措施实际上并未消减民办初中的“掐尖”特权。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;初级中学属于国家规定的义务教育，暂不论初中掐尖的合法性，我们分析一下是否合理。义务教育阶段的青少年处于身心发展的关键时期，应该以养成性教育为主，注重人格的培养。人生各个阶段知识积累的高度并非线性，青少年时期知识积累曲线比较平缓，进入高中阶段后曲线陡增，知识的深度广度明显增加，25岁以后大学毕业，进入了知识应用阶段。知识应用的有效性不取决于义务阶段所积累的知识，你见过哪一颗卫星是靠小学阶段的四则运算发射成功的。但这并不意味着没有小学的四则运算也可以发射卫星，因为那是基础。所谓的基础知识是没有他不行，但也不是有了它就行的。有些知识具有重叠性，小学在学，中学在学，大学还在学，比如英语。小学从what&amp;rsquo;s your name开始教，中学还是，到了大学也有。那么，小学可能要花一周的时间也未毕能记好，但到了大学只要你用一次你就记住了，你觉得哪个划算。浪费青少年的美好、快乐童年去学一些本不该他们学的东西是否划算（深恶痛绝的奥数及各类型的辅导班），有可能我们花费了百倍的精力，但没有收到一倍的效果。过早地启动竞争机制对儿童的身心发展极为不利。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我们不反对民办教育。民办教育搞得好，我们可能忽略了一个大前提，它采取了优先选择生源的措施。我们知道，人的智力发展水平不可能一模一样，一定存在一些学生其接受水平比同龄人要高，再加上超纲教育，民办学校获得高升学率就不足为怪了。那是谁纵容了“掐尖”这一现象的发展呢，我觉得还是家长。是家长望子成龙的焦急心态导致了这一现象的发生。试想多少年前，XX中学一开始的北大、清华升学率也不见得有多高，但突然有一年，冒了个尖，由此在坊间传开，XX中学了不起，家长竞相将孩子往里面送，学校的录取条件逐年提高，直到有资本叫板公立学校乃至教育局。所谓的良性循环其实是一种恶性竞争。能花大价钱将孩子送进去的家庭想必家庭条件很优越，是学校造就了学生，还是学生造就了学校，这是个悖论，正所谓是鸡和蛋的问题。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我们以一个平常心看待自已的孩子，他只是个普通人，不是50亿中的乔布斯或是比尔盖茨，也不是13亿人中的马云，他将来更可能只一名普通的社会分子。这样看来，他读不读XX中学对他的影响不大，因为将来大学毕业后他与普通中学毕业的学生所处的起跑线是一样的，一样要融入社会，过一般人的生活，上班、下班、生孩子、洗尿布再加工锅碗瓢盆。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;一个社会，如果教育成了谋利的手段，必将造成非常恶劣的后果。教育是个长期投入的系统工程，不可能立竿见影，当然其坏的影响也不是立即能显现的。社会上形形色色的辅导班，为什么会存在，因为有市场，有需求。事实上，这些机构完全不是在育人，只是在灌输知识，作为灌输知识的“机器”，其实电脑就会，而且比它做得更好。所以我的观点是，现在学生学不好不是没有资源，而是没有&lt;strong&gt;利用资源的能力和自制力&lt;/strong&gt;。书才是人类最好的老师，具备了识字的能力，剩下要做的只是读书，而不是上辅导班。对信息的利用也要辩证，不是获得的所有信息都是正确的，也可能会误导你。马丁路德金有一句关于教育的名言，“教育的功能是教给人们广泛且辩证地进行思考（The function of education is to teach one to think intensively and think critically）”。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;人才很少是培养出来的，人才是被唤醒的。教育的作用就是唤醒学生，因为他们本已很聪明，你不需要给他过多的知识，这些知识在他需要时自己会吸取。真正好的教育是对话，不是讲授。衡量人才的标准不是是否当官，不是腰缠万贯，古语所谓“立德、立功、立言”的人生三不朽才是人生最高境界。读书人应以胸怀天下为已任，不应简单地以谋生为追求。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;回到开篇的话题，尽管我们资源有限，每人都有享受良好教育资源的权利，但也付出了相应的代价。关键是付出的代价还未必有回报，不可能每人都能上理想的学校。这些代价不一定是金钱，更多的是家长的精力和孩子逝去的童年。我们允许精英教育，但精英教育的数量必须控制，不能让所有的家长都在步精英的后尘，最后还落了一场空。因此&lt;strong&gt;建议教育局&lt;/strong&gt;，规定民办学校的招生规模缩小为原来的10%，借读费名码标价50万元起步，让更多优秀的生源进入公立中学（因为大多数家长只是普通工薪阶层），解放更多的家长，不再为掏能力范围的20万（具体价格不明）不忍又无耐。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;悲乎教育，痛乎教育！悲哉家长，痛哉家长！&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Farewell to RPEMS</title>
      <link>https://kivinchoa.github.io/oneblog/posts/farewell/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2018 23:17:35 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kivinchoa.github.io/oneblog/posts/farewell/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To all the teachers in RPEMS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeff from class 607 will leave RPEMS and would like to appreciate your teaching last year. He spent wonderful time in this great school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeff is from Xi&amp;rsquo;an city in China. He came to RPEMS at his fifth grade on Feb 2017. At the beginning, he can not understand the teachers in the class. He learned English as the second language from Ms. Goldenberg. After half year, he entered into the sixth grade, I am glad that he can understand most words of teachers and classmates. He can communicate with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of this semester in September, Mr. Zimmermann gave him a book titled /Roll of Thunder, Hear My Cry/. I encouraged him to read it 10 pages everyday according the teacher&amp;rsquo;s requirements. He read it and listening the records. Finally he completed it. He found the interests from reading. From that on, he began reading a lot. He also read Chinese traditional novel. He has completed reading /Romance of the Three Kingdoms/, a 14th-century Chinese historical novel. Later as assignment, Mr. Zimmermann gave him another book titled /Walking on the Moon/. After reading, he got 100% score from test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He likes mathematics. He can calculate fast because he practice a lot in China. Ms. Calalang often praised him. In this semester, IXL was used to assign homework after class. At beginning, Jeff don&amp;rsquo;t like it at all because score can be reduced 10 points after only one error. Sometimes he repeated it many times for final 100 percent by spending more than two hours. Now he is used to it and likes it. When he is back home, he firstly completes the IXL homework. He know he can get 100 percent only if he works hard on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geography is the most difficult course for Jeff. He has no background about the geography. There are many terms what he never heard about. He did not complete homework very well at the first quarter of this year round. Later I taught him by interpreting the files attached on Edmodo by Mr. Williamson. He got broad knowledge from Middle East to Africa at the class of geography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science is another interesting class. Jeff learned matter state, atom, element periodic table and so on. Jeff completed a project about buoyant force. He surfed the internet, watched vedio from YouTube, and read downloaded documents. He did experiments to test if the hot water has the lower buoyant force compared with the cold water by use of bottled water floating in the basin. Finally he got the expected conclusion from the experiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.E. has no homework. Jeff learned how to play 5 different balls. But he can not get basketball because he is not tall enough. He said he can run very fast in 3 minutes with no stop. Sometimes he felt muscle ache after P.E. I told him that&amp;rsquo;s very common after exercising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeff took ESOL class twice or three times each week charged by Ms. Goldenberg. He made big progress after one year&amp;rsquo;s English learning. He likes ESOL class. He made good friends in this class. Ms. Goldenberg would collect talking pieces from students and encourage them to discuss them thoroughly in the class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth to mention that Jeff took part in the North Bay Camp. He often mentioned the experience in North Bay. He likes it very much. That&amp;rsquo;s the first time for him to leave us by himself. I know that he must do some stupid thing in that time. But he really grown up since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally Jeff and our whole family would express our heartful appreciation to all the teachers in RPEMS again. We got wonderful experience from RPEMS. Living here for one year would be the most unforgettable experience for us. We hope you living a joyful and healthy life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best regards,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeff and his family&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>